The Software Engineering Radio, episode
3, interview with Doug Schmidt.
Welcome to this episode of Software
Engineering Radio. This is Markus
Völter. Unlike the previous two
episodes, this one is one of our
interviews.
Our guest today is Douglas C. Schmidt.
Doug is a professor of computer science
at the Vanderbilt University. He focuses
on middleware, distributed real-time
embedded systems. He's actually the
father of the ACE ORB and the ACE
middleware below it. Doug is also
well-known for his work in the patterns
community. He is co-author of the
Pattern-Oriented Software Architecture,
volume 2 book, uh which deals with
patterns for concurrent and distributed
objects. More recently, Doug has been
focusing on the integration of
model-driven software development and
middleware. He has written a guest
editorial in this February's edition of
IEEE Computing. It provides a nice
summary on Doug's view on these topics.
At the OOP 2006 conference in Munich, I
gave a tutorial together with Doug on
the state of the art of model-driven
software development. The evening before
the tutorial, we got together in a hotel
room and recorded the interview. Have
fun.
Doug, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio. Why don't you start by explaining
a little bit about your personal
background and and what you do in in
real life? Thanks, Markus. I appreciate
your interviewing me. Uh first of all,
I've been a professor for the last
decade or so at Washington University in
St. Louis and University of California,
Irvine and at the now at Vanderbilt
University. But in some sense, that's
really just my my hobby. And what I like
to do most is spend time working with
people building systems, building
software, building open source software,
using the software for building actual
applications. And I managed to get into
this field sort of through an unusual
route. My original background was in
sociology, which is the study of human
organizations and and behavior and
structure of of organizations.
When I got done with my bachelor's and
master's degree in sociology, I realized
that while I enjoyed it intellectually,
there was very little way to make a
living doing those kinds of things. So,
I managed to get into a PhD program in
computer science at University of
California, Irvine, where I got my PhD
in software engineering and networking.
And when I finished up my degree, I I
realized that a lot of very smart people
had thought about networking topics for
a long time. And so, I decided to focus
instead on what in those days was the
beginnings of what we now call
middleware. And so, when I went to be a
professor at Washington University in
1994, we started doing a lot of work on
middleware. In fact, one of the very
early sponsors of our work was
the German company Siemens, in
particular the group up in Erlangen that
does work on medical engineering
solutions.
You mainly work in the domain of
distributed real-time embedded systems
or DRE systems. Can you tell us a little
bit about those systems and the
particular challenges in developing
them?
There a number of different definitions
of what a DRE system is. One of my
favorites is a DRE system is a system
where the right answer returned too
becomes the wrong answer. And there
there systems like
shipboard computing or avionics or
process control, manufacturing, even to
some extent things like financial
services and parts of telephony and
other domains along those lines where if
you get the information there too late,
it doesn't have much value for its user,
either because
the stock has changed price and you've
bought something too high or too low or
because the device you were trying to
control in the physical world has been
destroyed because you were able you were
unable to to prevent it from moving in a
direction you didn't like.
The characteristics we've been looking
at most recently have really been on
so-called enterprise distributed
real-time embedded systems or enterprise
DRE systems. These would include things
like uh supervisory control and data
acquisition systems for power grids,
total ship computing environments,
large-scale
information uh command and control
systems, and so on. And these types of
systems are characterized by the latency
and jitter requirements that you might
expect from a real-time embedded system,
low latency and very predictable low
jitter, as well as also having
characteristics of being highly scalable
that you might expect from an enterprise
distributed system. And these kinds of
systems are extremely difficult and
complex to build if for no other reason
that people often don't have a very good
idea of how they're supposed to behave
until they have them largely uh fielded,
which means that any mistakes and
problems that they have in the design
and the architecture and the
implementation are often done so far in
the life cycle that's very difficult to
try to improve them and uh
evolve them and optimize them to work
properly. So, a lot of the work that
we've been doing over the past several
years has been developing technologies
both based on on middleware, that is
run-time platforms that help take away
some of the complexity of trying to
program applications manually, as well
as combining them with with model-based
techniques, which try to raise the level
of abstraction, so people work with
abstractions that are closer to the
domain as opposed to being close to the
technology, you're close to the solution
space.
And these particular kinds of
abstractions are very important because
they allow us to be able to do what's
called speculative computing, where you
can do all kinds of what-if analysis to
understand very early on what the
characteristics and quality of service
of the system will be even if you don't
have all the parts finished and
complete. And we found that these kinds
of systems also tend to motivate the
need for a lot of advanced R&D
capabilities because they are simply far
beyond the grasp of any individual or
any team to solve with traditional ad
hoc, proprietary, and very manually
intensive software development
technologies.
So, I guess in a nutshell, the kinds of
systems that we work with interface a
lot with the real world and also have
information systems aspects to them as
well. And trying to balance the
trade-offs between the constraints of of
real-world processes and real-world
control with the kinds of complexities
that arise in information technology and
information systems is one of the
characteristics that make the enterprise
DRE domain so challenging and and so
rich as a place to explore. If we look
at the term DRE, then the D means
distributed. So, I guess the middleware
in those systems plays an important
role. So, can you explain a little bit
the role of middleware as kind of the
backbone of these systems, I suspect?
Sure. If you look at the way people used
to build real-time embedded systems, it
gives a good uh understanding of why
these domains are so hard. Historically,
people have built these kinds of systems
by putting the applications directly on
top of of hardware, if you go back far
enough. And perhaps over the last 10-15
years, what people typically have done
is they've built the applications
directly on top of of operating systems,
initially proprietary cyclic executives
and more recently off-the-shelf
operating systems, things like VxWorks
or LynxOS or QNX. Uh and one of the
characteristics as as these systems get
larger and more integrated and more
distributed is you find that there's a
lot of things that are required in order
to make these systems work that
typically are not part of the experience
and expertise base of people who have
domain knowledge, the the systems
engineers, the software architects, or
the software developers in those
domains. And so, what we were observing
over the past decade or so was that many
times people would try to build these
larger-scale distributed real-time
embedded systems, they'd often get stuck
because they didn't have the right
expertise in house to match the the
low-level platforms and protocols to the
operating systems and hardware and the
buses and so on with the knowledge of
the domain artifacts, things like
heads-up display or route planning and
navigation, if you're in the avionics
domain, or being able to do various
kinds of sensor management and planning
and filtering and track correlation, if
you're in the in the shipboard computing
domain, and so on. And so, what was
really needed was was some kind of
technology layer or layers that sits on
top of the operating system, on top of
the network, on top of the buses and the
hardware, but below the specific
application services that are part of
the the domain space.
When we first started looking at
middleware back in the early to mid
'90s, people didn't really have a good
idea of what it it looked like. It was
just kind of a blob that that somehow
linked things together. And people had
examples in those days of things like,
say, Sun RPC or or the
distributed computing environment DCE
from the Open Software Foundation.
As people began to do more work, uh in
particular as a lot of the researchers
joined in in some of the early efforts
on CORBA, it became clear that there
were actually a number of layers in the
middleware stack, just like there are a
number of layers in, say, the OSI stack
for network protocols or the TCP/IP
internet stack for protocols.
Some of the the layers people typically
associate with middleware these days
range from what's often called host
infrastructure middleware, which is
essentially an abstraction of the
operating systems and their different
heterogeneous APIs. If you think of an
operating system, it's basically a a
silicon abstraction layer. It's
abstracting
the higher-level services and
applications from the details of the
underlying hardware.
But the problem, of course, is that
there's so many different operating
system APIs to choose from. Even within
the Windows family, there's seven or
eight different variants. Within Linux
and and Unix, there's dozens of
different variants, not to mention the
the dozen or so common real-time
embedded systems as well. And so, as a
result, we need something to abstract
away from that. So, my early work was on
this host infrastructure middleware
abstraction in the form of something
called ACE, the Adaptive Communication
Environment. And ACE provides for the
C++ world what Java Virtual Machine and
the Java Class Libraries provide for the
Java world or the the CLR and the the
Microsoft Class Libraries and and Win32
encapsulations like Microsoft Foundation
Class provides for the Windows platform.
It provides a way of being able to write
at a higher level of abstraction that's
not so tightly coupled to the details of
any one platform.
And this provides things like event
demultiplexing, synchronous and
asynchronous communication, data
transfer, synchronization, locking,
concurrency control, threading,
processes, managing of various kinds of
of system resources in a platform
independent way.
It turns out, of course, if you start
trying to build systems that are going
to be connected over a network, you need
more than just those basic host
infrastructure middleware encapsulation
building blocks. You really need to have
something that's often known as
distribution middleware. And
distribution middleware's purpose in
life is to try to preserve a
common
programming paradigm, say an
object-oriented paradigm or a
component-based paradigm or a
service-oriented paradigm, and make it
look to the application developers on
the client and server side like they're
they're making method calls on on local
objects when in fact they're actually
making calls on proxies and they're
using some kind of broker implementation
of the broker pattern to glue together
the the various parties in the
communication path. So, distribution
middleware includes things like CORBA or
Java Remote Method Invocation or even
DCOM back in the Microsoft days.
Basically, broker abstractions that that
make it easier to pretend as though
you're programming standalone systems
when in fact you're talking across a
network.
The next layer up that's worth
characterizing is what's often known as
common middleware services. As you start
building distributed systems, you'll
find that there's certain services that
are common and reusable but very
powerful and and help to reduce a lot of
effort that otherwise goes into
reinventing things from scratch. So,
directory and naming services and
discovery services, event services,
fault tolerant services, service for
handling various kinds of security
issues, resource management, load
balancing, and so on. These are things
that are often reusable by many
different applications. Not all, of
course, but by many of them.
And it turns out that this is one of the
more interesting areas of middleware
these days and there's a lot of work
going on both in the research world and
in the commercial world trying to find
the right abstractions for these
services.
The the last layer of middleware that
it's worth characterizing in a generic
sense is is what I often term
domain-specific middleware.
The other layers, the the host
infrastructure middleware, the
distribution middleware, and the common
middleware services are all things that
you could expect to find off the shelf
or or eventually will find off the shelf
as the APIs stabilize and the
implementations mature.
The dis- the domain-specific middleware,
in contrast, are things that you don't
necessarily find off the shelf because
they really constitute the the
intellectual property, they they
constitute the value-added capabilities
that come from companies and groups that
work very deeply within a particular
domain. So, if you work in avionics, for
example, you'll have a tremendous amount
of knowledge of things like autopilot or
route and navigation planning or
heads-up display or various kinds of
management of devices and sys- And those
types of capabilities would be very
different from the kinds of
domain-specific entities you'd get if
you were doing some kind of process
control system or a financial services
system. And so, what you typically find
is that the domain-specific services are
reusable but their scope is much more
localized to a particular vertical
application domain.
And I think in the long run, this is
where a lot of the interesting work
remains to be done, not only in terms of
the middleware but also in terms of the
supporting tools and languages that help
make the middleware easier to apply for
domain-specific
applications. I think we'll talk a bit
more about this when we get to the topic
of of domain-specific uh modeling
languages. Yeah, sure. We'll we'll cover
that later. So, before we get there, I'd
like to get back to the middleware,
specifically to CORBA. Um in the
non-embedded world, um
I get the impression that CORBA has gone
out of fashion and things like the CORBA
Component Model have never caught on in
the embed- in the enterprise world. So,
I think I've Yeah, I think that's
different in the embedded world. You use
CORBA in your most of your systems,
right?
We actually do a number of things. We
we've diversified over the years. We do
work now on middleware platforms that
involve CORBA. Of course, that's been
our our bread and butter for about a
decade or so. We also do work some work
on CORBA Component Model. I'll talk more
about that in a second. But we also do a
lot of work these days on the OMG's Data
Distribution Service, which is a very
efficient pub/sub mechanism that has
very nice features that go above and
beyond what you're going to find with
with standard CORBA today. For example,
the OMG DDS, as it's called, has support
for
so-called meta events. You can subscribe
to the creation of new topics. You can
subscribe to the creation of new
subscribers. You can subscribe to the
creation of new publishers. You can also
subscribe to events like
network has been partitioned or quality
of service that was requested is no
longer be achieved due to various
overload conditions and so on. And this
makes it possible to build much more
dynamic systems that can learn the
characteristics of the environment in
which they run.
Other characteristics that DDS has that
are an improvement over CORBA is that
they really represent a de-layered
approach to pub/sub. Whereas in CORBA,
pub/sub is done as as a layered service,
the event service, the notification
service, and so on, built on top of the
orb. With DDS, the the pub/sub mechanism
is the orb in a sense and the orb is is
subsumed by those those mechanisms for
doing publish/subscribe. The other thing
that
DDS has that's really quite interesting
and and a lot of our
research is consumed without these days
has to do with the myriad, the number of
quality of service parameters. There's
about two dozen different quality of
service parameters that DDS supports
dealing with things like reliability and
resource constraints and history and
trading off reliability with timeliness
and giving coherent views on changes to
to data structures that are sent across
in a pub/sub manner, doing various kinds
of deadline scheduling requests and
latency budgets, and so on.
And this goes far beyond what you would
expect to find out of CORBA or even
real-time CORBA for that matter. And
this is very powerful, but it also means
that there's a lot of issues related to
optimization and certification to ensure
that all the different suppliers and
consumers in the system that are
tweaking and turning their quality of
service knobs to different settings end
up with coherent results.
So, we're really quite excited about DDS
as a sort of the next step and we've
been collaborating very closely with a
number of different DDS providers,
including Prism Technologies and uh
Real-Time Innovations and
uh Objective Computing Inc., OCI, all of
whom provide different DDS
implementations.
Uh we've also been doing some work on
Enterprise Java Beans and particularly
trying to extend some of the deployment
configuration mechanisms and and
services provided by the CORBA Component
Model through model-driven techniques to
work appropriately in the world of of
EJB and and J2EE as well. So, oh, and I
should also mention that one of our
students spent an internship at
Microsoft recently. So, we also have
some .NET work going on.
Here's kind of the way I I look at the
world these days. I think I think you're
absolutely right, Marcus, that in the in
the classic enterprise world, that the
sort of the transaction systems,
e-commerce side, it's it's no it's
pretty clear that
CORBA's no longer the new kid on the
block and there's a lot of other
technologies that have become very
fashionable in those environments,
particularly lately things like web
services and service-oriented
architectures.
Where I see CORBA still having a lot of
value, though, is in two areas. One, of
course, is in in DRE systems,
which are often characterized by the
need to be able to have very long
lifespans and the need to be able to
integrate lots of different technologies
running on many different platforms over
long periods of time with many different
languages and many different
characteristics and technology bases.
And and CORBA is really about the only
game in town these days that that
satisfies most of those needs. It's it's
a standard, you get multiple
interoperable implementations from
different suppliers. It works on many,
if not all, operating systems if you
take a look at the totality of the orbs
that are available. It works on many
different programming languages. And so,
a lot of people in in those domains who
who look at things from a a
5-to-10-to-20-year perspective really
like CORBA for that reason. And of
course, it also, especially in the C++
and C bindings, focuses on quality of
service and low latency and and high
throughput and and good predictability.
So, I think CORBA's got a a very bright
future in that space. And you see this
reflected in terms of things like
software-defined radio, where it's it's
very widely used, and in a lot of the
aerospace and defense industries, where
it's also very widely used. It's also
very widely used in the telecom industry
as well.
One other place that's worth just
noting, because sometimes we forget
about this
in our in our pursuit of of the big or
the small, is just the the mainstream
client-server applications that need to
send information across a distributed
system or a network. The kind of places
where people used to use, say, RPC or
DCE.
What I find, especially because of the
the maturation and the
ubiquity of good, low-cost or even free
implementations of CORBA, often
open-source implementations, a lot of
people doing just sort of
general-purpose computing that requires
network connectivity often find CORBA a
very nice solution. I find this
especially in places like China and
India and other countries where they
have a lot of computing infrastructure
that they're in the process of putting
together and they don't have to worry
about a big installed base and they are
trying to to avoid uh, they're trying to
hedge their bets by keeping their
platform choices open. So, we see a lot
of people at least using our middleware
from all around the world, and I don't
think they're using them for for classic
enterprise systems, but they're not
using them for embedded systems either.
They're using them for sort of this
general-purpose computing that is tied
together with network types of
applications. But, um,
the the good news is that as we get
better support for higher-level
abstractions, things like
domain-specific modeling languages,
which we'll talk about later, to some
extent the specific choice of middleware
platform becomes less important. It's
always important, of course, becomes
less important or less strategic, and
the choice of the right abstraction for
programming and integration becomes more
important. So, where I hope we're going
to be in 5 years or so is CORBA will be
one piece of our overall portfolio of of
R&D and and product activities, but a
lot of that stuff will be subsumed by
generators out of domain-specific
modeling technologies. You mentioned
open-source implementations of CORBA.
Uh, one of them is the the TAO, ORB,
which you kind of invented or built
initially.
Um, do you want to maybe tell our
listeners a little bit about how this
has developed, how where it's used, and
how it's how it evolves today? Sure. Uh,
when I was a professor at Washington
University, we'd been working on this
this ACE host infrastructure middleware
technology for a number of years. I
started working on that actually while I
was a grad student in California. And it
found its way onto some interesting
projects. It found its way into the the
Motorola Iridium project, which was
quite a revolutionary product for the
project for the day. It found its way
into some uh various
private branch exchange switches and and
central office switches from Ericsson
and some other folks.
And at first we were we were sort of
skeptical that CORBA was even the right
thing to do because we we did a lot of
benchmarking in the early days and found
that the early implementations of CORBA
were were unbelievably inefficient. They
had lots of extra memory copies and
a lots of extra locks and and overhead
from threading and other sources of
inefficiency and and hazards and so on
from scheduling point of view.
And about uh 1997 or so, we had built up
enough infrastructure in the form of ACE
that we decided we would actually see if
we could take all the experience we'd
learned and gained benchmarking the
CORBA implementations to see what was
wrong with them, and actually try to do
a better job of implementing them than
the kinds of things that were available
at that time. So, we took the the
patterns that we'd learned and and that
later got documented in the POSA 2 book,
and we took the the frameworks that we
developed for ACE and the wrapper
facades we developed for ACE, and we
arranged them to implement a version of
CORBA, which we called the ACE ORB,
pronounced TAO.
And this took a couple of years to
really get off the ground. At first it
was as as most beta and alpha software
is, big and slow and clunky and and full
of bugs. But, uh, one of the great
things about the open-source community
is that you've got a lot of really smart
people all around the world focusing
their brainpower on improving that
technology base. And we got some really
innovative contributions from all over
the place. We got a guy from uh
Colombia,
uh, South America, who contributed some
super-optimized event demultiplexing
logic that we put into our our reactor
framework in ACE, which sped up the ORB
inner loops considerably. We we had some
people down in uh
Santiago, Chile, contribute some
interesting optimizations for encoding
and decoding of uh the common data
representation of CORBA using assembly
language instructions to avoid memory
copies. And And over the years a lot of
very very talented people from the
United States and all around the world,
uh, including Germany, contributed lots
of interesting things. And uh as a
result, as of circa 2000-2001, we had an
ORB that was competitive in terms of
features and competitive in terms of
performance with most of what was
available commercially at that point.
Uh, around that time a number of
companies, including Prism Technologies
and Objective Computing Incorporated and
more recently companies like like Remedy
in the Netherlands, started to support
TAO and and ACE for that matter using a
commercial support model not unlike what
say Red Hat or Cygnus before them had
done for the GNU tools. And that's when
things really started to take off
because we were able to get a lot of uh
another bright minds who were able to go
in and improve the software. A lot of
companies started to pick it up at that
point, including uh major projects at at
many aerospace companies, Boeing,
Lockheed, Raytheon, as well as many uh
commercial companies. If if you look at
almost any Fortune 500 company there or
or telecom company, there's probably
some TAO poking around there somewhere.
And uh this has ended up allowing us to
create a fairly complete and faithful
and efficient implementation of of
almost the entire CORBA 2.x spec and
almost the most of the so-called
lightweight CORBA Component Model or
CORBA 3.0 spec, uh 3.x spec. And that's
where a lot of our focus is these days,
finishing off some of the implementation
aspects that go into the CORBA Component
Model as it pertains to the the profile
that was stripped down
removing things like transactions,
removing things like persistence, to
make it a little smaller, to make it a
lot more predictable and fast for the
distributed real-time embedded world.
So, it's it's been quite an interesting
experience being involved not just from
a research point of view in an ivory
tower-like sense just looking for new
innovations and publishing papers, but
also trying to make sure that the
quality of the software that we
developed was sufficient that people
could use it for
bet-your-company mission-critical types
of systems. One of the things that we've
learned along the way is that to be
successful in this area, it's crucial to
have automated support for quality
assurance. And I think this is actually
an observation that most successful
larger-scale open-source projects like
Linux or the GNU projects and so on have
discovered. You've got to find some way
to be able to take advantage of all
those spare computing cycles available
in the user community and all those
thousands of eyeballs to focus them on
solving problems that have to do with
places that may not otherwise be
exercised through normal smoke testing
that people do when they put out their
their open-source releases. So, we've
spent a lot of time researching in
collaboration with colleagues at
University of Maryland
and uh a couple of other companies,
including Raytheon and Lockheed Martin,
ways of being able to automate large
amounts of the QA. And uh we've got it
to the point now where we can actually
run a very large amount of test cases in
a distributed environment using
techniques not unlike the SETI@home
project that runs uh search for
extraterrestrial signal uh
contacts through people's screensavers
in their spare time. So, I think that
the take-home point I've I've learned
from this experience over the last
decade or so is that you can produce
very high-quality software if you're
willing to uh take the time to try to
automate the distributed continuous
quality assurance and build processes.
You've already mentioned the term
pattern, and you've you're also a
co-author of POSA 2, the Pattern
Oriented Software Architecture Series,
Volume 2, about Distributed and
Concurrent Objects. I think that's the
the the subtitle. So, uh maybe you want
to elaborate a little bit about uh the
use of patterns in in in this kind of
systems. There's actually a kind of a
funny story about that. Um, back in 1993
when I was finishing up my PhD at UC
Irvine, I happened to be doing two
things at the same time. I was learning
the Orbix implementation of CORBA, which
was used very heavily on the Motorola
Iridium project I mentioned earlier. And
I was also a reviewer for the the Gang
of Four book, the Design Patterns
Catalog. And uh what was so fascinating
about this is as I was reading that
Design Patterns Catalog book, I began to
realize that the patterns I was seeing
described in this book, which by the way
had not been published yet, things like
chain of responsibility or proxy or
bridge or strategy,
these were all the same kinds of
abstractions I was seeing as I was
looking at the Orbix source code. And it
really struck me how profound this
pattern concept was because clearly
these these developers often Dublin,
Ireland, such as Chris Horn and and Hugh
Grant and some of the other people who
developed the early Orbix
implementations, had come upon the same
design techniques even though they'd
never seen the book on patterns, which I
thought was quite quite eye-opening at
the time. And I remember thinking at
that point I was I was kind of stuck at
a crossroads in my life whether I wanted
to go to be a professor or whether I
wanted to do consulting and and work in
industry. And I remember thinking I
would really like to be able to go on
and at least spend enough time in the
academic setting to to figure out what
types of patterns would be applicable
for things like say distributed systems
and network systems and network
applications. Didn't really know that
much about middleware those days, but I
guess if I thought about it I would have
used the word middleware. And I wanted
to to take some time to to learn them
and write them down. And the ironic part
was over the next say 5 to 7 years of my
life, I spent a lot of time developing
software, working with companies like
Siemens and Boeing and many many other
different groups, and learning these
patterns and and having the fortune of
working with many bright students and
colleagues like uh Frank Buschmann and
Michael Stal and Michael Kircher at
Siemens, and actually finding ways to to
document these these patterns, and then
at the same time building middleware and
building network applications that could
actually try them out in practice. So,
as it turned out, one of the reasons why
we were able to create such a large
amount of software things like ACE and
TAO now are around 2 million lines of
C++ code that run on dozens of different
operating systems and compilers. One
reason why we were able to build such a
large amount of software and keep it
going for so long with quite frankly a
rather shoestring budget for a long
time, was because we were able to
leverage the architectural insights that
came from using the patterns that we
discovered through other work. And that
became crucial to help bring new people,
new grad students, new staff, new
members of the ACE and TAO community
into the fold, as it were, and to guide
them, to explain to them what the
architecture of the system was based on,
and then explain to them in pattern form
what the constraints were, what the
trade-offs were, and and help them use
those patterns as effectively as
documentation to to make good design
decisions. And I don't think we could
have done it having not had the the
pattern information.
Now, as we've moved on since those days,
a lot of that work culminated in the in
the POSA two book,
uh we've learned a lot of other things.
In fact, one of the things we've learned
recently is
how you can take patterns for
optimization and use them to do
so-called specializations
of the middleware. What There's a
classic tension when you build any kind
of reusable software between the
generality needed to get the maximum
number of users happy on the maximum
number of use cases and the specificity
that comes from wanting to make the
software as uh fine-tuned and optimized
for the particular context in which it
runs. And for a long time people have
had to choose one of those two
ends of the spectrum. They either built
things from scratch to be highly
specialized or they would build things
in a very reusable way, in which case
they were often very inefficient. So,
what we've been doing lately is working
with various kinds of of aspect-oriented
approaches and other kinds of techniques
like such as partial evaluation and
coming up with uh domain-specific
languages and tools that let let us take
our general-purpose frameworks and be
able to customize them for particular
details of the underlying platforms, of
the underlying um environments, and of
the use cases the application developers
are using. And this, of course, is yet
another way of looking at patterns.
You're looking for patterns of
invariants. What things stay the same?
What things change? A good example would
be something like the event
demultiplexing mechanism that's used in
most ORBs.
In uh the case of something like the ACE
ORB, there's about a half dozen or so
different event demultiplexers that
could possibly be used when you build
the ORB. You could have
a win- a Windows wait for multiple
objects event demultiplexer. You could
have a select-based demultiplexer. You
could have a uh a poll-based or
dev/epoll-based
or kqueue demultiplexer and so on and so
forth. And and no one right size is
right all the time. So, we of course
built a framework called the reactor
that lets us plug in different
demultiplexers.
Well, the interesting truth is that in
most applications, even though you might
want the flexibility of having different
event demultiplexers for different
applications in a product line, perhaps,
you only need one at a time. So, rather
than hard-coding the software, instead
we come up with some clever
domain-specific language techniques we
can use to annotate our reactor
framework implementation so that when we
know specifically the details of a
particular event demultiplexing
environment, we can automatically strip
out all the extra virtual function calls
and inheritance and indirection and
replace
the dynamic binding calls with inlined
calls that are statically bound. And
this saves a good, you know, 5 to 10% of
overhead on on, you know, large
amounts of data and and large amounts of
uh information that's sent across the
system. And all kinds of similar
techniques can be used for things like
customizing the demarshaling and and
marshaling mechanisms, coming up with
smarter ways to handle exception
handling, and um avoiding going through
excessive numbers of layers multiple
times, and doing various kinds of
pooling and caching and so on.
So, once again, patterns are really
about looking for commonality and
extracting it out of a world that can
often be variable and finding ways to
find ways to make the variability have a
common interface. And so, it's it's kind
of exciting to see the the whole field
evolve away from simple design patterns
to things that are also heavily
optimization-driven to allow not just
behavioral and structural
characteristics, but also quality of
service characteristics and design
expertise to be leveraged and improved.
Something you mentioned before was the
term model and domain-specific languages
and and generation and these kinds of
things. So, um most people probably have
heard about the MDA, model-driven
architecture from the OMG. So, I wonder
uh how you use modeling and code
generation, all these kinds of kind of
hype topics in in distributed uh
real-time systems. That's a that's a
great question.
When I try to understand this to myself
and I try to explain it to other people,
I usually start by pointing out that the
last 40 years of computing have been an
inexorable movement away from uh
implementation and solution-centric ways
of looking at the world, things that are
bound up with computers and and networks
and and very low-level things like
register allocations and things like
that, towards abstractions that are
closer to the designer's intent. And if
you look for the first, you know, 20
years or so, it was a movement away from
uh very low-level platforms like like
hardware uh to to operating systems and
executives. If you can also think, of
course, the transition away from machine
code to assembly language to
second-generation languages like C. That
represents an abstraction
uh away from the solution space closer
to the application problem domain space.
The problem is uh severalfold, though.
Unfortunately, despite lots of advances,
in many ways we're we're still kind of
stuck in the following mire in a lot of
these areas. In terms of of platforms,
we've managed to create much more
sophisticated platforms that use
frameworks and class libraries and
components and so on in in the terms of
middleware. But those are now becoming
so complex that that very few people
really have a lot of experience in
making them work in the large.
At the same time, the complexity of the
platforms has
drastically or drastically outstripped
the complexity or the sophistication of
programming languages that can be used
to simplify the access to those
platforms and the manipulation of the
platform abstractions. So, if you think
about things like uh C++ and Java and
C#, those are all clearly
more uh shall we say, in quotes,
high-level abstractions relative to C or
assembly code, but they pale in
comparison to the kinds of complexities
that can occur when you try to build
these very large-scale systems using
frameworks and and middleware.
And so, what's really happened here is
that language evolution hasn't kept up
with platform evolution over the last,
say, decade or or at least the last
decade. A lot of my friends who do
programming language research claim that
there really hasn't been much of an
innovation in programming languages over
the past 20 to 25 years.
So, what what do we need to do? Well, I
guess one way to look at this is that
the notion of a general-purpose
uh
one-size-fits-all programming language
that can be applicable to all different
use cases and domains has kind of
reached a point of diminishing returns.
C#, Java, C++, and all the libraries
that go along with those things
represent kind of the the last hurrah of
that paradigm of development. And if you
really want to go further, you have to
start getting into much more
domain-specific, much more vertical
kinds of things.
Well, there's a couple of different ways
of going about this. Uh the model-driven
architecture approach was an attempt by
the OMG to try to deal with the
cacophony, the the diversity of
heterogeneous platforms and languages
that has arisen, especially in the
enterprise domain, over the past 10 to
15 years.
And the goal there was to try to come up
with some abstractions, things like
structure diagrams, to represent classes
and their relationships, things like
state charts to represent behavior and
and the uh transition between various
kinds of control flows within systems,
or the action semantic language, ASL,
which is a way of trying to represent
behavior again in a in a sort of an
imperative-like way.
And to do this in a manner that didn't
really uh
impinge on or didn't really have any
uh particular binding to one platform or
one language, to make things platform
and language-independent.
And the of course the the goal here was
to try to make it easier for people to
build systems that weren't going to be
so wrapped up in the details of the
underlying uh technology infrastructure.
There are a lot of good things to be
said about this approach. It it tries as
much as it can to leverage pretty widely
understood things like the the Unified
Modeling Language and and the notions of
syntax and and semantics implied
therein.
But the problem with with MDA, in my
mind, is it doesn't really go far
enough. It really provides just a small
layer of abstraction and a slight
distance and a raise of the level of
abstraction away from building
applications using third-generation
languages with conventional platforms.
True, you don't use C++ or Java
directly, per se,
but what you program with, which is is
usually something like ASL, which which
looks, for my money, awful an awful lot
like Visual Basic or Pascal, uh it's not
that much different. It's not really
raising the paradigm that much.
Likewise, whether you use classes versus
UML structure diagrams to describe the
the roles and relationships between the
structure of your solution and your
software architecture, it's really not
that drastically a different level of
abstraction. In a sense, what you're
really doing is you're working with
domain-independent
modeling languages, or perhaps
domain-dependent, but the domain is the
domain of general-purpose computing. So,
you're not really raising the level of
abstraction very much.
And so, while people have had some
interesting successes in this area, I
think a far more fruitful long-term
direction is to use what's known as
domain-specific modeling languages,
which try to use various techniques such
as metamodeling, which is also often
known as concept modeling, and the
notion of uh
uh domain-specific modeling languages
that represent things more in the way
that the users or the systems engineers
or the domain experts tend to think
about the problem,
and and capture them at a much higher
level of abstraction, and then through
some type of transformation engine or
code generator or interpreter, create
the artifacts that map onto the
underlying level or levels or layers of
abstraction, which could be middleware
platforms, could be operating systems
directly, could even be the hardware in
some cases. And so, you're you're left
with many more degrees of freedom to go
from the high level to the low level.
Now, one of the thing that's really
important to recognize here is that uh
with a domain-specific perspective,
we're often not necessarily competing
head-to-head with the traditional
programming techniques for the kinds of
things that programming techniques do
well.
Programming techniques such as Java or
C++ or C# or or even the the action
semantic language for that matter
are pretty good at representing
behaviors. Yes, you can come up with
with formalisms that are are useful for
certain very limited domains like state
machines, but they're not that bad often
times to be able to characterize the
control flow and and the way in which
information has to flow through a
system.
In contrast, however, there are an awful
lot of things, especially in large-scale
systems
where
conventional third-generation
programming languages are
wholly unsatisfying and unsuitable for
being used in any large-scale way. And
and often times you don't realize this
stuff until you've got yourself into a
pickle by trying to build very
large-scale systems where those systems
have uh characteristics that you you
don't see if you're focusing on the the
trees and not the forest. For example,
if you try to put together a system with
two or three components
dependencies and deployment issues and
configuration and customization issues
aren't very profound. In contrast, if
you try to put together a system with a
thousand or ten thousand components,
you've got a major integration problem
on your hands. And conventional
techniques for dealing with this using
XML or C++ or Java are very non-scalable
for the main reason that they don't
represent the uh
they don't represent the solution in a
way that represents a mapping back to
the problem that's being addressed.
So, in those areas, domain-specific
modeling languages or or domain-specific
languages for short are actually very
satisfying very suitable because they
help to represent the specific
information that's important for that
level of abstraction shielding people
from things that they don't need to know
about or don't need to know about in
full detail at at any given point in
time and allowing people to come back
later and enrich and annotate further
the information as they gather it. And
so, these domain-specific modeling
languages are far more declarative than
imperative and they can take advantage
of all kinds of analysis and synthesis
uh synthesis techniques in order to
reduce the probability of error through
so-called correct-by-construction
techniques as well as to be able to
uh greatly reduce the amount of code
that has to be written manually by
humans, but instead can be generated by
by an automated machine. Uh this again
should come as no surprise. We've been
doing this for 40 years if you think of
a compiler for a language like C++ or
Ada or Java uh that generates something
for a lower-level abstraction like 68000
assembly code or uh RISC instruction
set. It's the same basic idea. It's just
about going between levels of
abstraction. Now, we're moving the
levels of abstraction further up towards
the domain space as opposed to being
stuck down in the solution space.
I'm actually very uh excited about this
particular perspective because I think
we're getting to the point now where
systems are sufficiently complex
and people are trying to deploy them in
sufficiently broad topology environments
that it makes sense to really pay
attention to some of these other issues
that heretofore received somewhat short
shrift from the development processes
and tools and environments that we
worked with.
Uh
so, I think we're we're getting to a
point where this is quite exciting. I
should also mention something else that
in addition to looking at at structural
and behavioral aspects of software
model-based approaches and
domain-specific modeling languages are
also increasingly relevant for dealing
with issues related to the the quality
of service issues. And I'll give you a
quick example.
If you build large-scale systems,
systems that often have hundreds or
thousands of people working on them for
tens of years or dozens of years and
often have um uh large amounts of of
infrastructure that has to be developed
before the applications can be built you
run into what I call the the serialized
phasing problem where you have this
chicken and egg problem where you can't
fully evaluate the performance and the
quality of the infrastructure you're
building until the applications are
sufficiently done to exercise them. And
of course, you can't build the
applications until you've got the
infrastructure fully developed or at
least enough developed that you can
actually build the applications and run
them.
And this uh this chicken and egg problem
is actually quite serious for many
large-scale systems and I've seen many
many systems fail over time. Uh the the
Iridium project comes to mind because
they spent so much time building
infrastructure that they didn't have a
chance to get the applications done and
by the time they got the applications
done, the infrastructure's flaws with
respect to being non-scalable or
uh error-prone or or having problems
with fault tolerance or security don't
manifest themselves in a way that you
can actually correct in a time and uh
cost-effective manner.
So, one of the things we've been looking
at lately is the use of of model-driven
development techniques and
domain-specific languages for
system execution modeling, which
basically allows you to develop very
quickly using model-based tools um
faux or uh or sort of uh
application component generators that
can be assembled very rapidly to behave
as though they were the real application
components and they have all the same
properties you would have with the
application codes again about interfaces
with ports. You can wire those ports
together with modeling tools and so on.
And you can put these things together
very quickly to create experiments to
run on the actual target infrastructure
in order to be able to evaluate and ask
kind of what if questions. What if I
arrange the deployment and configuration
in a certain way? What will that do to
my average and worst-case uh execution
time for the critical path? Where are
the bottlenecks in the system? How many
calls per second can I get through this
particular part? What kinds of
replication schemes work best under
different loads and so on.
And uh these techniques, which really
only work if you have effective support
for rapid prototyping of application
behavior that comes from higher-level
modeling technologies, are crucially
important in being able to get that
information quickly.
The the last piece of the puzzle I'll
mention in the space of of modeling
approaches has to do with combining
modeling with model checking and static
analysis of the software for various
properties.
One of the problems that's often plagued
people who build C and C++ applications
and unfortunately, for better or for
worse most DRE systems today are still
built with C and C++
uh they have a very hard time being able
to do any kind of analysis of the code
properties because C and C++ are rather
uncivilized languages with all kinds of
quirks in terms of pointer aliasing and
memory corruption and and other weird
things that don't show up and and when
they do show up, uh they end up causing
havoc for analyzers of the software
unless they're very very sophisticated.
And so, one of the nice things about
using model-based approaches is they can
be far more civilized cuz they have
better properties in terms of their
semantics and and the behaviors that
they exhibit. And so, as a result, you
can do a lot more analysis on the models
often than you can do on the code. And
especially if you're able to then
forward engineer the code from the
models then you can hopefully have
better confidence that what you're
creating through the constructive
process will be more likely to be
correct than today's
construct-by-correction processes where
we build software by repeated testing
until things break and then we go back
and scratch our heads and wonder how to
fix it.
So, I think there's a a wonderful
synergy between model-based approaches
and the wonderful base synergy between
patterns and frameworks and middleware
and just as uh the last 10 years has
seen the synergy between frameworks and
class libraries and patterns as people
got smart about patterns they got smart
about frameworks. They got smart about
middleware. I think the same thing is
happening as we get smart about
modeling, we're getting smart about how
we build middleware and some of the
quirks in the middleware platforms can
be shielded from developers and it
allows them to work at a higher level of
abstraction that is ultimately more
satisfying although the the jury is
still out in terms of getting a lot of
the accidental complexities wrangled out
of that technology mix. So, but you're
not doing MDA officially, you're doing
something different. Maybe two sentences
of how you character characterize that?
We're we're not really doing MDA in the
the executable UML sense. If if you look
at MDA as a technology standard, uh then
we're not really doing MDA the
technology standard. If you look at MDA
the the philosophy of building systems
based with higher-level abstractions
that shield you from the details of
lower-level platforms and languages,
we're we're definitely doing that. Uh in
fact, I think it's fair to say that the
the OMG over time has begun to realize
the the deficiencies with their initial
MDA approach and they've actually stood
up a new
um special interest group called the
Model Integrated Computing Special
Interest Group. If you go to
mic.omg.org,
you'll find information about the MIC
group. And they're actually looking at
what you do to come up with standards
for model-driven development, model
integrated computing which is really
more based on this notion of
domain-specific modeling languages
rather than domain-independent modeling
languages, which is really what UML and
executable UML are. Now, just just a
quick word on this. In order to keep
domain-specific modeling languages and
technologies from collapsing under their
own weight we ultimately have to get to
the point where we have common, ideally
standard tools and environments for
building domain-specific modeling
languages. If if everybody has a
different domain-specific modeling
language and a different domain-specific
modeling language environment we're not
much better off than we were 30 years
ago when everybody and their brother had
a different programming language and uh
they didn't interoperate and and they
were very expensive and everybody had
their own little dialect that no one
else knew how to speak or use.
So, I think that we're we're by no means
done here, but I think we're going to
see a a great proliferation of
domain-specific modeling languages as
generator technology and metamodeling
environments get more mature
and from those explorations, we're going
to start to codify
good practice that manifests itself in
terms of domain-specific languages for
particular domains where people have
enough critical mass to start to
standardize what those things should
look like. And there's a bunch of
different efforts coming out of the
Eclipse Foundation, coming out of
Microsoft, coming out of a number of
different open source groups, which
gives me great confidence that we'll
have enough of a community and enough of
a experience base in place by the time
that people are really interested in
using this technology for for real
systems.
So before we finish off, I'd like to
briefly come back to your hobby of being
a professor for computer science. How do
you integrate your students into your
work? I always read papers from you that
have a lot of students as co-authors and
they're integrated into all that ACE and
middleware and and research and
practical research work. How is the way
What's the way of integrating them?
One of the things my my PhD advisor once
said is the only way way to be really
successful as a professor is to teach
the people around you how to do what you
know how to do so you can leverage their
experience and their brainpower and
their their time and energy in order to
multiply your productivity. And so I've
always been a big believer in trying to
get my students involved in as many of
the kinds of real world activities that
I've been involved in as a consultant
and an author and a system developer and
a researcher over the last two decades.
We do we have the fortune of working
with a lot of companies that are work.
Many Many research projects tend to do
things where they're funded by
government sponsorship agencies that
that really focus on a novelty which of
course is important research almost at
the exclusion of practicality and and
transition. And while that's certainly a
lot of fun and we do some of that
ourselves, I've often found it even more
interesting and challenging and and
rewarding to focus on how you take those
novel ideas and actually go the next
step which is to translate them out of
the world of the ivory tower into the
world of commercial practice. I find
that there's some really rewarding
challenges and some interesting
opportunities that come as a result of
that. So an awful lot of our research
funding comes from working with with
companies like like Siemens or
Qualcomm, Cisco, Veritas, Symantec. We
we've worked with most of the telecom
companies at one time along the way or
another. We've even worked with
Microsoft at various points. We've also
done a lot of work with companies like
large scale system integrator companies
like Boeing and Raytheon and and
Lockheed Martin. And doing this gives
the students a much deeper appreciation
of what really has to get done in the
real world to take these ideas out of
the laboratory and off the off the paper
website into the actual code. We've also
been very fortunate that we've built up
a huge body of software and there's a
lot of people who aren't my grad
students but are people who are part of
our community of of open source
middleware and modeling developers and
users who contribute substantially in
order to be able to provide a good role
model for the students. So the students
learn very very early on the importance
of
quality control, using build
environments, using source code control
systems, not breaking the builds, using
things like distributed continuous
quality assurance to run the
their their code on many different
platforms before they commit it to make
sure the software works. And and having
an open source community where there are
literally thousands of people around the
world who who will quickly find your
flaws in your software and and beat you
back into submission to fix it has been
quite an educational experience. And I
think a lot of the students when they
graduate come away with a
much deeper appreciation than the
average graduate student would about
what needs to be done in the real world
to make stuff work.
But of course because they're
researchers and they're they're rewarded
ultimately by the quality and the
quantity of the papers and the ideas
they produce, they're also kind of
pushed in that direction as well. So I
think this is a a very good thing. The
other thing that I should mention too is
at least in the United States right now
in general there's a downturn in the
number of people going into computer
science. There's a perception
probably somewhat misguided that that
somehow all the good jobs are being
outsourced to other places with lower
lower labor rates and stuff like that.
And while it's certainly the case that
the general purpose computing jobs are
probably going to places with lower
labor rates, it is also the case that
the mission critical systems, the
systems where you bet your business,
where you have life and safety critical
and mission critical objectives that
must be met without fail where the where
the right answer too late is the wrong
answer, those kinds of jobs have a
tendency not to be offshored and
outsourced so glibly. And what we're
finding is that students who have those
types of expertise are quickly snapped
up by all kinds of different people
because there really isn't much more
there really isn't there really aren't
many places that are producing those
kinds of people number one and number
two there's a tremendous demand within
the United States and I suspect also
within other countries like like Germany
and in Europe for people with very deep
expertise in things like mission
critical, safety critical, distributed
real time embedded systems. So what I
always tell my students is
these domains may be a little harder,
you may have to work longer hours to
become an expert and master them
but the good news is that you're a lot
more recession proof and you're a lot
more outsource outsourcing proof when
you have those kinds of skills.
Thomas Friedman in his book The World is
Flat talks about a job category he
refers to as the untouchables.
And he says the untouchables are
basically people who for whatever reason
are very hard to to replace with other
folks. He uses examples of course like
Michael Jordan, the famous basketball
player,
or people who are
great musicians or scientists as
examples. But also of course you have
people who are who are experts in their
profession. And my experience has been
that everybody who who really learns
through the the baptism of fire in an
environment that pushes both novel
research ideas and the
transformation of those novel ideas into
real systems that actually work are
often in very good position when they
graduate. So we've been pretty pretty
fortunate be able to attract very bright
people because they realize that this is
a good investment in their long-term
career path. Last question.
Short one. Many of your projects are in
the defense area. Many of your slides
show those jet fighters and stuff. Have
you ever had the chance to fly in one
and would you like to?
Actually I've I've never had a chance to
fly in in a real one but there's some
really interesting flight simulator
software that you can get access to that
that makes
What is it? Flight Commander by
Microsoft pale in comparison. There's a
couple of domed simulators that they
have in in places like Boeing and I've
had the
uh
the exciting time of being able to sit
in one of those and fly those and boy is
it it amazing. What's even more exciting
of course is is realizing that that our
software is being used as the basis for
a lot of that stuff. A lot of the the
simulate distributed interactive
simulation software in the world based
on things like the the HLA RTI, the high
level architecture runtime
infrastructure is all based on ACE and
TAO. So it's it's very rewarding. But I
remember
remember one time one of my students who
who got his PhD recently went to to
Italy and he's working for a company
there that's basing that's basically
building the next generation air traffic
control system in Europe using ACE and
TAO. And I always like to joke with him
that I I might take the train for a
while until they get all the bugs out of
the system. But
they often say that there's no better
proof of of someone's confidence in
their code than to to fly with it.
And I think we're we're no exception.
But
yes, we we definitely try to do as many
different things in different domains as
possible and the the course the places
that are interesting to work are the
ones with all the hard problems so they
tend to be the ones we focus on. Okay
Doc, I really want to thank you for the
interview tonight. Thank you Marcus and
thank you again for inviting me to to
spend some time with you tonight.
This concludes our interview with Doc
Schmidt.
Thanks for listening. I hope you enjoyed
this show. For more information on some
of the topics and abbreviations and
concepts he talked about, take a look at
the show notes.
See you next week.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio.
For general information and past
episodes, go to www.se-radio.net.
SE Radio wants to thank Henning Pauli
for providing the music we use in this
show.